This is the first in a five
video series on potatoes.
In this series we'll look
at the glycemic index,
how best to cook them and
which potato is the best.
"Do Potatoes Increase
the Risk of Diabetes?"
The trouble for white
potatoes began in 2006,
when the Harvard Nurses’ Health
Study, which had followed
the diets and diseases of tens
of thousands of women for 20 years,
found that greater potato
intake was associated with
a greater likelihood of
getting type 2 diabetes.
Okay, but wait. Of the hundred
or so pounds of potatoes
Americans eat every year,
most are in the deep-fried form
of potato chips or French fries.
What happened when they looked
specifically at mashed or baked potatoes?
They found the same link with diabetes.
Okay, but what might
potato eaters eat more of?
I’ll give you a hint by rephrasing that as:
what might meat-and-potatoes
people eat more of?
Indeed, people who ate
more potatoes ate more meat,
and we know that animal
protein on its own
is associated with
increased diabetes risk.
But the researchers tried
to statistically adjust
for that and still found
increased risk with potatoes.
Well, what do people put
on baked and mashed potatoes?
Butter and sour cream. Again,
the researchers tried to adjust
for other dietary factors
like these as well as effectively
looking at the ratio
between plant and animal fats,
and whether potato
eaters drank more soda,
or maybe skimped on other
vegetables, and still
there seemed to be this
potato diabetes association.
Okay, but that was just one study.
By 2015, Harvard researchers had
also looked into other cohorts,
including the all-male Health
Professionals Follow-up Study
to complement the all-
female Nurse’s studies,
and they continued to find a
small increased diabetes risk
associated with baked,
boiled, or mashed potatoes,
though French fries do indeed
appear nearly five times worse.
The authors concluded that
potatoes are considered to be
a healthy vegetable
in dietary guidelines;
however, the current ﬁndings cast
serious doubts on that classiﬁcation.
Walt Willet, the chair of Harvard’s
nutrition department at the time,
went a step further, suggesting potatoes
should be siloed up there with candy.
A meta-analysis of potato consumption
and risk of type 2 diabetes
published in 2018 combined all
six of the prospective studies
that has been done to date, and they
found about a 20 percent increase
in diabetes risk associated with
each serving of potatoes a day,
concluding long-term high
consumption of potato may be
strongly associated with
increased risk of diabetes.
But, again, the great majority of
this potato consumption was fried,
and we know there are all
sorts of nasty things like
advanced glycation end
products in deep fried foods.
The researchers weren’t able to assess
French fries versus non-fried potatoes.
Even just three servings of
fries a week is associated
with nearly 20 percent greater
risk of type 2 diabetes,
whereas there was only a
tiny associated risk with
potatoes in general, and that
included the fries mixed in.
The world’s largest manufacturer
of frozen French fries
took issue with this conclusion,
laying claim to one in three
fries eaten on planet Earth
to the tune of billions of
dollars, they have the money
to fund reviews like this one
to cast doubt on the science.
But they do have an actual point.
Observational studies can
never prove cause-and-effect,
and maybe potato consumption,
even baked potato consumption,
may just be a marker for an
unhealthy diet in general.
As much as researchers try to
adjust for these other factors,
as the journal of the Potato Association
of America is quick to remind us,
it’s not possible to completely
separate the effects
of potatoes and French
fries from the effects
of the overall crappy
Standard American Diet.
If only there was a country
where potato consumption
was associated with a healthy diet.
If potato consumption was still
associated with diabetes there,
then that would be concerning.
But here we go...a seventh study,
but this time out of Iran,
where not only is most of their potato
consumption from boiled potatoes,
but those who eat potatoes had
the healthiest diets and ate
the most whole plant foods—fruits,
vegetables, whole grains, and beans.
And though the researchers
tried to tease out those other
dietary factors, those eating
the most boiled potatoes had
only half the odds of
developing diabetes.
This supports the notion that it may be hard
to completely separate out just the potatoes.
The bottom line, this systematic
review concluded, is that
we really don’t have convincing
evidence to date that the intake
of potatoes in general is
linked to type 2 diabetes,
but we should still
probably hold the fries.